Funding for this program is provided by
Additional funding provided by
Today we turn to John Locke.
On the face of it, Locke
is a powerful ally of the libertarian.
First, he believes, as libertarians today maintain,
that there are certain fundamental individual rights
that are not just for the libertarian.
They are so important that no government,
even a representative government,
even a democratically elected government,
can override them.
Not only that, he believes
that those fundamental rights include
a natural right to life, liberty, and property.
And, furthermore,
he argues that the right to property
is not just the creation of government or of law.
The right to property is a natural right
in the sense that it is pre-political.
It is a right that
attaches to individuals as human beings.
Even before,
even before government comes on the scene,
even before parliaments and legislatures enact laws
to define rights and to enforce them.
Locke says in order to think about
what it means to have a natural right,
we have to imagine the way things are
before government, before law.
And that's what Locke means by the state of nature.
He says the state of
nature is a state of liberty.
Human beings are free and equal beings.
There is no natural hierarchy.
It's not the case that some
people are born to be kings
and others are born to be serfs.
We are free and equal in the state of nature.
And yet,
he makes the point that there's a difference
between a state of liberty and a state of license.
And the reason is that
even in the state of nature,
there is a kind of law.
It's not the kind of law that legislatures enact.
It's a law of nature.
And this law of nature constrains what we can do
even though we're free,
even though we're in the state of nature.
Well, what are the constraints?
The only constraint given by the law of nature
is that the rights we have,
the natural rights we have,
we can't give up.
Nor can we take them from somebody else.
Under the law of nature,
I'm not free to take somebody else's life
or liberty or property.
Nor am I free to take my own life
Even though I'm free,
I'm not free to violate the law of nature.
I'm not free to take my own life
or to sell myself into slavery
or to give to somebody else
arbitrary absolute power over me.
So where does this constraint,
you may think it's a fairly minimal constraint,
but where does it come from?
Well, Locke tells us where it comes from.
And he gives two answers.
Here's the first answer.
For men,
being all the workmanship
of one omnipotent and infinitely wise maker,
namely God,
they are his property.
Whose workmanship they are
made to last during his,
not one another's, pleasure.
So one answer to the question is
why can't I give up my natural rights
to life, liberty, and property is,
well, they're not strictly speaking yours.
After all, you are the creature of God.
God has a bigger property right in us.
A prior property right.
Now you might say that's
an unsatisfying, unconvincing answer,
at least for those who don't believe in God.
What did Locke have to say to them?
Well, here's where Locke appeals to the idea
of reason.
And this is the idea
that if we properly reflect
on what it means to be free,
we will be led to the conclusion
that freedom can't just be
a matter of doing whatever we want.
I think this is what Locke means
when he says,
the state of nature has a law of nature
to govern it which obliges everyone.
And reason, which is that law,
teaches mankind who will but consult it
that all being equal and independent,
no one ought to harm another in his life,
health, liberty, or possessions.
This leads to a point
where Locke's idea of
reason is a puzzling, paradoxical feature
of Locke's account of rights.
Familiar in one sense,
but strange in another.
It's the idea that our natural rights
are unalienable.
What does unalienable mean?
It's not for us to alienate them
or to give them up,
to give them away,
to trade them away,
to sell them.
Consider an airline ticket.
Or tickets to the Patriots
or to the Red Sox.
Non-transferable tickets
are unalienable.
I own them in the limited sense
that I can use them for myself,
but I can't trade them away.
So in one sense,
an unalienable right,
a non-transferable right,
makes something I own
less fully mine.
But in another sense
of unalienable rights,
especially where we're thinking
about life, liberty, and property,
for a right to be unalienable
makes it more deeply,
more profoundly mine.
And that's Locke's sense
of unalienable.
We see it in the American Declaration
of Independence.
Thomas Jefferson drew on this idea
of Locke.
Unalienable rights,
to life, liberty,
and as Jefferson amended Locke,
to the pursuit of happiness.
Unalienable rights.
Rights that are so
essentially mine
that even I can't trade them away
or give them up.
So these are the rights we have
in the state of nature
before there is any government.
In the case of life and property,
I can't take my own life,
I can't sell myself into slavery
any more than I can take
somebody else's life
or take someone else
as a slave by force.
But how does that work
in the case of property?
Because it's essential
to Locke's case
that private property
can arise
even before there is any government.
How can there be a right
to private property
even before there is any government?
Locke's famous answer
comes in section 27.
Every man has a property
in his own person.
This nobody has any right to
but himself.
The labor of his body
and the work of his hands,
we may say,
are properly his.
So he moves
as the libertarians later
would move
from the idea
that we own ourselves,
that we have property
in our persons,
to the closely connected idea
that we own our own labor.
And from that
to the further claim
that whatever we mix
our labor with
that is unowned
becomes our property.
Whatever he removes out of the state
that nature has provided
and left it in,
he has mixed his labor with
and joined it to something
that is his own
and thereby makes it his property.
Why?
Because the labor
is the unquestionable property
of the laborer
and therefore no one
but the laborer
can have a right
to what is joined to
or mixed with
his labor.
And then he adds this important provision,
at least where there is enough
and is good left in common
for others.
But we not only
acquire a property
in the fruits of the earth,
in the deer that we hunt,
in the fish that we catch,
but also
if we till and plow
and enclose the land
and grow potatoes,
we own not only the potatoes
but the land,
the earth.
As much land
as a man tills,
plants, improves,
cultivates,
and can use,
the product of
so much is his property.
He by his labor
encloses it
from the commons.
So,
the idea that rights are unalienable
seems to distance Locke
from the libertarian.
The libertarian wants to say
we have an absolute property
right in ourselves
and therefore we can do with ourselves
whatever we want.
Locke is not a sturdy ally
for that view.
In fact, he says if you take
natural rights seriously,
you'll be led to the idea
that there are certain constraints
on what we can do
with our natural rights,
constraints given
either by God
or by reason,
reflecting on what it means
really to be free.
And really to be free
means recognizing
that our rights are unalienable.
So here's the difference
between Locke and the libertarians,
but when it comes
to Locke's account
of private property,
he begins to look again
like a pretty good ally.
Because his argument
for private property
begins with the idea
that we are the proprietors
of our own person
and therefore of our labor,
and therefore of the fruits
of our labor,
including not only the things
we get,
which we gather
and hunt
in the state of nature,
but also we acquire
a property right
in the land that we enclose
and cultivate and improve.
There are some examples
that can bring out
the moral intuition
that our labor
can take something
that is unowned
and make it ours.
Though sometimes there are disputes
about this.
There's a debate
among rich countries
and developing countries
about trade-related
intellectual property rights.
It came to a head recently
over drug patent laws.
Western countries,
and especially the United States,
say we have a big
pharmaceutical industry
that develops new drugs.
We want all countries
in the world to agree
to respect the patents.
Then there came along
the AIDS crisis
in South Africa.
And the American AIDS drugs
were hugely expensive,
far more than could be afforded
by most Africans.
So the South African government
said we are going to begin
to buy a generic version
of the AIDS antiretroviral
drug at a tiny fraction
of the cost
because we can find
an Indian manufacturing company
that figures out
how the thing is made
and produces it.
And for a tiny fraction
of the cost,
we can save lives
if we don't respect that patent.
And then the American government
said, no, here's a company
that invested research
and created this.
Right?
And they said,
we're going to buy
a generic drug.
You can't just start
mass producing these drugs
without paying a licensing fee.
So there was a dispute.
And the US,
the pharmaceutical companies
sued the South African government
to try to prevent their buying
the cheap, generic,
as they saw it,
pirated version of an AIDS drug.
And eventually,
the pharmaceutical industry
gave in and said,
all right, you can do that.
But this dispute
about what the rules
of property should be,
of intellectual property,
of drug patenting,
in a way,
is the last frontier
of the state of nature
because among nations
where there is no uniform law
of patent rights
and property rights,
it's up for grabs
until, by some act of consent,
some international agreement
that people enter into
some settled rules.
What about Locke's account
of private property
and how it can arise
before government
and before law comes on the scene?
Is it successful?
How many think
it's pretty persuasive?
Raise your hand.
How many don't find it persuasive?
All right, let's hear
for some critics.
What is wrong with Locke's account
of how private property
can arise without consent?
Yes.
Yeah.
I think it justifies
European cultural norms
as far as,
when you look at
how Native Americans
may not have cultivated
American land,
but by their arrival
in the Americas,
that contributed
to the development of America,
which wouldn't have otherwise
necessarily happened then
or by that specific group.
So you think
that this is a defense,
this defense of private property
in land?
Yes, because it complicates
original acquisition
if you only cite
the arrival of foreigners
that cultivated the land.
I see.
And what's your name?
Rochelle.
Rochelle?
Yeah.
Rochelle says,
this account of how property arises
would fit what was going on
in North America
during the time of the European settlement.
Do you think, Rochelle,
that it's a way of defending
the appropriation of the land?
Indeed, because he's also
justifying the Glorious Revolution,
so I don't think it's inconceivable
that he's also justifying colonization.
Well, that's an interesting
historical suggestion,
and I think there's a lot
to be said for it.
What do you think of the validity
of his argument, though?
Because if you're right
that this would justify
the taking of land in North America
from Native Americans
who didn't enclose it,
if it's a good argument,
then Locke's given us
a justification for that.
If it's a bad argument,
then Locke's given us
a mere rationalization
that isn't morally defensible.
I'm leaning to the second one.
You're leaning toward the second.
But that's my opinion as well.
All right, well then,
let's hear if there's a defender
of Locke's account of private property,
and it would be interesting
if they could address Rochelle's worry
that this is just a way
of defending the,
of appropriation of land
by the American colonists
from the Native Americans
who didn't enclose it.
Is there someone who will defend Locke
on that point?
You ready?
Are you going to defend Locke?
You're accusing him of justifying
the European, basically, massacre
of the Native Americans.
But who says he's defending it?
Maybe the European colonization isn't right.
You know, maybe it's the state of war
that he talked about
in his second treatise, you know?
So the wars between the Native Americans
and the colonists, the settlers,
that might have been the state of war
that we can only emerge from
by an agreement or an act of consent,
and that's what would have been required
fairly to resolve it.
Yeah, and both sides would
have had to agree to it
and carry it out and everything.
But what about, and what's your name?
Dan.
Dan, what about, Rochelle says,
this argument in Section 27 and then in 32
about appropriating land,
that argument, if it's valid,
would justify the settlers appropriating that land
and excluding others from it.
Do you think that argument's a good argument?
Well, doesn't it kind of imply
that the Native Americans hadn't already done that?
Well, the Native Americans, as hunter-gatherers,
didn't actually enclose, enclose land.
So I think Rochelle is onto something there.
What I want to, I'd like to...
Go ahead, Dan.
At the same time, he's saying that
just by picking an acorn or taking an apple
or maybe killing a buffalo
on a certain amount of land,
that makes it yours because it's your labor
and that's, you know, your labor
would enclose that land.
So by that definition,
maybe they didn't have fences around,
around little plots of land but didn't...
They were using it.
Yeah, by Locke's definition.
So maybe by Locke's definition,
the Native Americans could have claimed their property right
in the land itself.
But they just didn't have Locke on their side,
as she points out.
Okay, that's good.
One more defender of Locke.
Go ahead.
Well, I mean, just to defend Locke,
he does say that there are some,
sometimes in which you can't take another person's land.
For example, you can't acquire land
that,
that is common property.
See, people in,
in terms of American Indians,
I feel like they already have civilizations themselves
and they were using land in common.
So it's kind of like what,
an analogy to what he was talking about with like,
the common English property.
You can't take land that everybody's sharing in common.
Oh, that's interesting.
And also you can't,
you can't take land unless you make sure that there's
as much land as possible left
for other people to take as well.
So if you're taking common,
so you have to make
sure that whenever you take land
or that there's enough land,
that there's enough left for other people to use.
That's just as good as the land that you took.
So.
That's, it's, it's true.
Locke says there has to be this
right to private property in the earth
is subject to the provision that there be as much
and as good left for others.
What's your name?
Right.
I'm Fang.
So Fang in a way agrees with Dan
that maybe there is a claim within Locke's framework
that could be developed on behalf of the Native Americans.
Here's the further question.
If the right to private property is natural,
not conventional,
if it's something that we acquire
even before we agree to government,
how does that right constrain
what a legitimate government can do?
In order for us to be able to do that,
in order finally to see whether is,
whether Locke is an ally or potentially a critic
of the libertarian idea of the state,
we have to ask what becomes of our natural rights
once we enter into society.
We know that the way we
enter into society is by consent,
by agreement.
To leave the state of nature
and to be governed by the majority.
And by consent.
And by a system of laws.
Human laws.
But those human laws
are only legitimate
if they respect our natural rights.
If they respect our unalienable rights
to life, liberty, and property.
No parliament,
no legislature,
however democratic its credentials,
can legitimately violate our natural rights.
This idea
that no law can violate our right
to life, liberty, and property would seem
to support the idea of a government so limited
that it would gladden the
heart of the libertarian after all.
But
those hearts should not be so quickly gladdened.
Because even though
for Locke,
the law of nature persists
once government arrives,
even though Locke insists on limited government,
government limited by the end for which it was created,
namely the preservation of property,
even so,
there's an important sense
in which what counts as my property
what counts as respecting my life and liberty
are for the government to define.
That there be property,
that there be respect
for life and liberty
is what limits government.
But what counts
as respecting my life
and respecting my property,
that is for governments
to decide and to define.
How can that be?
Is Locke contradicting himself?
Or is there an important distinction here?
In order to answer that question,
which will decide Locke's fit with the law,
Locke's fit with the libertarian view,
we need to look closely
at what legitimate government looks like for Locke,
and we turn to that next time.
Nikolai, if you didn't think you'd get caught,
would you pay your taxes?
Um, I don't think so.
I would,
I would rather have a system, personally,
that I would, that I could give money
to exactly those sections of the government
that I support,
and not just blanket support everything.
You'd rather be in the state of nature,
at least on April 15th.
Last time,
we began
to discuss Locke's state of nature,
his account of private property,
his theory of legitimate government,
which is government based on consent
and also limited government.
Locke believes in certain fundamental rights
that constrain what government can do,
and he believes that those rights are natural rights,
not rights that flow from law.
Or from government.
And so Locke's great
philosophical experiment is to see
if he can give an account
of how there could be
a right to private property
without consent
before government
and legislators arrive on the scene
to define property.
That's his question.
That's his claim.
There is a way, Locke argues,
to create property,
not just in the things we gather and hunt,
but in the land itself.
Provided there is enough
and is good luck for others.
Today I want to turn to the question
of consent,
which is Locke's second big idea.
Private property is one,
consent is the other.
What is the work of consent?
People here have been invoking
the idea of consent since we began,
since the first week.
You remember when we were talking about
pushing the fat man off the bridge,
someone said,
but he didn't agree to sacrifice himself.
It would be different if he consented.
Or when we were talking about the cabin boy,
killing and eating the cabin boy.
Some people said,
well,
if they had consented to a lottery,
it would be different,
then it would be all right.
So consent has come up a lot,
and here in John Locke,
we have one of the great philosophers of consent.
Consent is an obvious, familiar idea
in moral and political philosophy.
Locke says that legitimate government
is government founded on consent,
and who nowadays would disagree with him?
Sometimes when the ideas of political philosophers
are as familiar as Locke's ideas about consent,
it's hard to make sense of them,
or at least to find them very interesting.
But there are some puzzles,
some strange features
of Locke's account of consent
as the basis of legitimate government,
and that's what I'd like to take up today.
One way to look at it,
one way of testing
the plausibility of Locke's idea of consent,
and also of probing some of its perplexities,
is to ask just what a legitimate government
founded on consent can do,
what are its powers according to Locke?
Well, in order to answer that question,
it helps to,
remember what the state of nature is like.
Remember, the state of nature
is the condition that we decide to leave,
and that's what gives rise to consent.
Why not stay there?
Why bother with government at all?
Well, what's Locke's answer to that question?
He says there are some inconveniences
in the state of nature,
but what are those inconveniences?
The main inconvenience
is that everyone
can enforce the law of nature.
Everyone is an enforcer,
or what Locke calls the executor
of the state of nature.
And he means executor literally.
If someone violates the law of nature,
he's an aggressor,
he's beyond reason,
and you can punish him.
And you don't have to be too careful or fine
about gradations of punishment
in the state of nature.
You can kill him.
You can certainly kill someone
who comes after you,
tries to murder you.
That's self-defense.
But the enforcement power,
the right to punish,
everyone can do the punishing
in the state of nature.
And not only can you punish with death
people who come after you,
seeking to take your life,
you can also punish a thief
who tries to steal your goods,
because that also counts as aggression
against the law of nature.
If someone has stolen
from a third party,
you can go after him.
Why is this?
Well, violations of the law of nature
are an act of aggression.
There is no police force,
there are no judges,
no juries.
So everyone is the judge
in his or her own case.
And Locke observes that
when people are the judges
of their own cases,
they tend to get carried away.
And this gives rise to the inconvenience
in the state of nature.
People overshoot the mark.
There's aggression.
There's punishment.
And before you know it,
everybody is insecure
in the enjoyment
of his or her unalienable rights
to life, liberty, and property.
Now he describes in pretty harsh
and even grim terms
what you can do to people
who violate the law of nature.
One may destroy a man
who makes war upon him
for the same reason
that he may kill a wolf
or a lion.
Such men have no other rule
but that of force and violence.
Listen to this.
And so may be treated
as beasts of prey
those dangerous and noxious creatures
that will be sure to destroy you
if you fall into their power.
So kill them first.
So what starts out
as a seemingly benign
state of nature
where everyone's free
and yet where there is a law
and the law respects people's rights
and those rights are so powerful
that they're unalienable,
what starts out
looking very benign
once you look closer
is pretty fierce
and filled with violence
and that's why people want to leave.
How do they leave?
Well, here's where consent comes in.
The only way to escape
from the state of nature
is to undertake
an act of consent
where you agree
to give up the enforcement power
and to create a government
or a community
where there will be
a legislature
to make law
and where everyone
agrees in advance,
everyone who enters,
agrees in advance
to abide by whatever
the majority decides.
But then the question,
and this is our question
and here's where I want
to get your views,
then the question is
what powers,
what can the majority decide?
Now here it gets tricky
for Locke
because you remember
alongside the whole story
about consent
and majority rule
there are these natural rights,
the law of nature,
these unalienable rights
and you remember
they don't disappear
when people
join together
to create a civil society.
So even once the majority is in charge
the majority can't violate
your inalienable rights,
can't violate your fundamental right
to life, liberty and property.
So here's the puzzle.
How much power
does the majority have?
How limited is the government
created by consent?
It's limited by
the obligation
on the part of the majority
to respect
and to enforce
the fundamental natural rights
of the citizens.
They don't give those up,
we don't give those up
when we enter government.
That's this powerful idea
taken over from Locke
by Jefferson
in the Declaration.
Unalienable rights.
So let's go to our two cases.
Remember Michael Jordan,
Bill Gates,
the libertarian objection
to taxation for redistribution.
Well what about
Locke's limited government?
Is there anyone who thinks
that Locke
does give grounds
for opposing taxation
for redistribution?
Anybody?
Go ahead.
If you,
if the majority rules
that there should be taxation,
even if the minority
should still not have to be taxed
because that's taking away property
which is one of the rights of nature.
Alright, so,
and what's your name?
Ben.
So,
if the majority taxed,
taxes the minority,
without the consent of the minority
to that particular tax law,
it does amount to a taking
of their property
without their consent
and it would seem that
Locke should object to that.
You're not going to object to that?
Do you want some textual support
for your view,
for your reading of Locke, Ben?
Alright.
I brought some along
just in case you raised it.
If you've got,
if you have your texts,
look at 138,
passage 138.
The supreme power,
by which Locke means the legislature,
cannot take from any man
any part of his property
without his own consent.
For the preservation of property
being the end of government,
and that for which men enter into society,
it necessarily supposes and requires
that people should have property.
That was the whole reason
for entering society in the first place,
to protect the right to property.
And when Locke speaks about
the right to property,
he often uses that
as a kind of global term
for the whole category,
the right to life, liberty, and property.
So, that part of Locke
at beginning of 138
seems to support Ben's reading.
But what about the part of 138
if you keep reading?
Men, therefore, in society,
having property,
they have such a right to the goods
which by the law of the community
are theirs.
Look at this.
And that no one can take from them
without their consent.
And then at the end,
of this passage, he says,
so it's a mistake to think
that the legislative power
can do what it will
and dispose of the estates
of the subject arbitrarily
or take any part of them at pleasure.
Here's what's elusive.
On the one hand, he says,
the government can't take your property
without your consent.
He's clear about that.
But then he goes on to say,
I mean, that's the natural right to property.
But then it seems to me
that property, what counts as property,
is not natural but conventional,
defined by the government.
The goods which by the law
of the community are theirs.
And the plot thickens
if you look ahead to section 140.
In 140, he says,
governments can't be supported
without great charge.
Government is expensive.
And it's fit that everyone
who enjoys his share of the protection
should pay out of his estate.
And then here's the crucial line.
But still it must be with his own consent,
i.e. the consent of the majority,
giving it either by themselves
or through their representatives.
So what is Locke actually saying?
Property is natural in one sense,
but conventional in another.
It's natural in the sense that
we have a fundamental right,
we have a fundamental, unalienable right,
that there be property,
that the institution of property
exist and be respected by the government.
So an arbitrary taking of property
would be a violation of the law of nature
and would be illegitimate.
But it's a further question,
here's the conventional aspect of property,
it's a further question,
what counts as property,
how it's defined,
and what counts as taking property,
and that's up to the government.
So the consent,
here we're coming back to our question,
what is the work of consent?
What it takes for taxation to be legitimate
is that it be by consent,
not the consent of Bill Gates himself
if he's the one who has to pay the tax,
but by the consent that he and we,
all of us within the society gave
when we emerged from the state of nature
and created the government
in the first place.
It's the collective consent.
And by that reading,
it looks like consent is doing a whole lot
and the limited government consent creates
isn't all that limited.
Does anyone want to respond to that
or have a question about that?
Go ahead.
Stand up.
Well, I'm just wondering what Locke's view is
on once you have a government that's already in place,
whether it is possible for people
who are born into that government
to then leave and return to the state of nature.
I mean, I don't think that
Locke mentioned that at all in the...
What do you think?
Well, I think as the convention,
it would be very difficult to leave the government
because you are no longer...
because nobody else is just
living in the state of nature.
Everybody else is now governed by this legislature.
What would it mean today, you're asking,
and what's the answer?
What's your name?
Nicola.
To leave the state...
Suppose you wanted to leave civil society today.
You want to withdraw your consent
and return to the state of nature.
Well, because you didn't actually consent to it.
You were just born into it.
It was your ancestors who joined.
Right.
So...
You didn't sign the social contract.
I didn't sign it.
Exactly.
All right.
So what does Locke say there?
Yeah.
I don't think Locke says
that you have to sign anything.
I think that he says
that it's kind of implied consent.
And by leaving and taking government services,
you are implying that you are consenting
to the government taking things from you.
All right.
So implied consent,
that's a partial answer to this challenge.
Now, you may not think that implied consent
is as good as the real thing.
Is that what you're shaking your head about, Nicola?
Speak up.
Stand up and speak up.
I don't think that necessarily
just by utilizing the government's...
you know, various resources that we are necessarily implying
that we agree with the
way that this government was formed.
Or that we have consented to
actually join into the social contract.
So you don't think the idea of implied consent
is strong enough to generate any obligation at all
to obey the government?
Not necessarily, no.
Nicola, if you didn't think you'd get caught,
would you pay your taxes?
Um...
I don't think so.
I would rather have a system, personally,
that I could give money to
exactly those sections of the government
that I support,
and not just blanket support everything.
You'd rather be in the state of nature,
at least on April 15th.
But, Nicola,
what I'm trying to get at is,
do you consider that you're under no obligation
since you haven't actually entered into any act of consent,
but for prudential reasons,
you do what you're supposed
to do according to the law?
Exactly.
If you look at it that way,
then you're violating another one of Locke's treatises,
which is that you can't take anything from anyone else.
Like, you can't take the government services
and then not give them anything in return.
If you want to go
live in the state of nature,
that's fine,
but you can't take anything for the government
because by the government's terms,
which are the only terms under
which you can enter the agreement,
say that you have to
pay taxes to take those things.
So you're saying that Nicola can
go back into the state of nature
if she wants to,
but she can't drive on Mass Ave.
Exactly.
I want to raise the stakes beyond using Mass Ave.
Yes.
And even beyond taxation.
What about life?
What about military conscription?
Yes.
What do you say? Stand up.
First of all, we have to
remember that sending people to war
is not necessarily implying that they'll die.
I mean, obviously, you're not raising their chances here,
but it's not a death penalty.
So if you're going to
discuss whether or not military conscription
is equivalent to suppressing people's right to life,
you shouldn't approach it that way.
Secondly, the real problem here is Locke has this view
about consent and natural rights.
But you're not allowed to
give up your natural rights either.
So the real question is, you know,
how does he himself figure it out
between I agree to give up
my life, give up my property,
when he talks about taxes
or military conscription for the fact,
but I guess Locke would be against suicide.
And that's still, you know, my own consent.
I agree to taking my life.
Eric.
So Eric brings us back to
the puzzle we've been wrestling with
since we started reading Locke.
On the one hand, we have these unalienable rights
to life, liberty, and property,
which means that even we don't
have the power to give them up.
And that's what creates the limits on legitimate government.
It's not what we consent to that limits government.
It's what we lack the power
to give away when we consent.
That's the point at the heart of Locke's whole account
of legitimate government.
But now you say, well, if
we can't give up our own life,
if we can't commit suicide,
if we can't give up our right to property,
how can we then agree
to be bound by a majority
that will force us to sacrifice
our lives or give up our property?
Is Locke at all convinced?
Does Locke have a way out of this?
Or is he basically sanctioning an all-powerful government,
despite everything he says about unalienable rights?
Does he have a way out of it?
Who would speak here in defense of Locke
or make sense, find a way out of this predicament?
All right, go ahead.
I feel like there's a general distinction to be made
between the right to life that individuals possess
and the fact that a government
cannot take away a single individual's right to life.
I think if you look at conscription as the government
picking out certain individuals to go fight in war,
then that would be a violation
of their natural right to life.
On the other hand, if you have conscription,
let's say a lottery, for example,
then in that case, I
would view that as the population
picking their representatives to defend
them in the case of war.
The idea being that since the
whole population cannot go out there
to defend its own right to property,
it picks its own representatives through a process
that's essentially random.
And then these sort of elected representatives
go out and fight for the rights of the people.
It works very similar,
it works just like an elected government, in my opinion.
All right, so an elected government can conscript citizens
to go out and defend the way of life,
the community that makes the enjoyment of rights possible?
I think so.
I think it can, because to
me it seems that it's very similar
to the process of electing representatives to a legislature.
Although here, it's as if the government is electing
by conscription certain citizens to go
die for the sake of the whole.
Is that consistent with respect
for a natural right to liberty?
Well, what I would say there is,
there is a distinction between picking out individuals
and having a random choice of individuals.
Between picking out, let me make sure,
between picking out individuals.
Well, by...
Let me, what's your name?
Gokul.
Gokul says there's a
difference between picking out individuals
to lay down their lives,
and having a general law,
I think this is the answer Locke would give, actually.
Gokul.
Locke is against arbitrary government.
He's against the arbitrary taking.
The singling out of Bill Gates
to finance the war in Iraq.
He's against singling out a particular citizen,
or group of people,
to go off and fight.
But if there's a general law,
such that the government's choice,
the majority's action is non-arbitrary,
it doesn't really amount to a violation
of people's basic rights.
What does count as a violation
is an arbitrary taking,
because that would essentially say,
not only to Bill Gates, but to everyone,
there is no rule of law.
There is no institution of property.
Because at the whim of the king,
or for that matter, of the parliament,
we can name you, or you,
to give up your rights,
or your property,
or to give up your life.
But so long as there
is a non-arbitrary rule of law,
then,
it's permissible.
Now you may say this doesn't amount
to a very limited government.
And the libertarian may complain
that Locke is not such a terrific ally after all.
The libertarian has two grounds
for disappointment in Locke.
First,
that the rights are unalienable,
and therefore I don't really own myself after all.
I can't dispose of my life,
or my liberty, or my property,
in a way that violates my rights.
That's disappointment number one.
Disappointment number two,
once there is a legitimate government
based on consent,
the only limits for Locke
are limits on arbitrary takings
of life,
or of liberty,
or of property.
But if the majority decides,
if the majority promulgates
a generally applicable law,
and if it votes
duly, according to fair procedures,
then there is no violation.
Whether it's a system of taxation,
or a system of conscription.
So it's clear that Locke
is worried about the absolute arbitrary power
of kings.
But it's also true,
and here's the darker side of Locke,
that this great theorist of consent
came up with a theory of private property
that didn't require consent.
That may,
and this goes back to
the point Rochelle made last time,
may have had something to do with Locke's second concern,
which was America.
You remember,
when he talks about the state of nature,
he's not talking about an imaginary place.
In the beginning, he says,
all the world was America.
And what was going on in America?
The settlers were enclosing land
and engaged in wars with the Native Americans.
Locke, who was an administrator
of one of the colonies,
may have been as interested
in providing a justification
for private property through enclosure
without consent,
through enclosure and cultivation,
as he was with developing a theory
of government based on consent
that would reign in kings
and arbitrary rulers.
The question we're left with,
the fundamental question we still haven't answered is,
what then becomes of consent?
What work can it do?
What is its moral force?
What are the limits of consent?
Consent matters not only for governments,
but also for markets.
And beginning next time,
we're going to take up questions
of the limits of consent
in the buying and selling of goods.
Don't miss the chance to interact online
with other viewers of Justice.
Join the conversation.
Take a pop quiz.
Watch lectures you've missed
and learn a lot more.
Visit justiceharvard.org.
It's the right thing to do.
Funding for this program is provided by...
Additional funding provided by...
The U.S. Department of State.